this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio net SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
or / software this March 21st and 22nd
don't miss technique night at Burlingame
California just minutes from the San
Francisco Airport come to techie 9 to
get rock-solid info on forecasts on
adaptive cybersecurity emerging
technologies machine learning and deep
level
operational intelligence and much more
join tech superstars Steve Wozniak and
Grady Booch plus sea level leaders from
Netflix Google IBM Salesforce GE digital
and Mattel to gain valuable insights and
learn about real world solutions you can
start applying today register now for
the I Triple E computer society's
premier conference tech impact at tech
ignite computer org and discover the
truth behind technology
for software engineering radio this is
Robert bloomin today I am here at the
Dropbox corporate headquarters in San
Francisco with James cowling James is
the storage team lead at Dropbox where
he was the architect of the magic pocket
distributed storage system his other
work includes consensus protocols
replication scalable infrastructure and
cluster management according to Wired
magazine cowling turned down a job
opportunity at Google in order to work
on this project James welcome to
software engineering radio thanks so
much glad to be here is there anything
else you'd like to tell the listeners
about your background
Havas is this a pretty-pretty charitable
buyer that you've given the listeners so
thank you for that I guess you can tell
the Australians so I'm from Australia
I've been at Dropbox for about five
years now and you know you came here at
an academia it used to be in research
and I came into industry and it's been a
great time ever since so yeah great
today I'd like to talk to you about
dropboxes migration off the cloud and
the magic market system that you built
to replace cloud services Wired magazine
did a piece on this called the epic
story of Dropbox's exodus from the
Amazon Cloud Empire we'll link to that
in the show notes and I'd like to
explore some themes from that article
and from your engineering blog to start
with describe Dropbox yeah so hopefully
most listeners know what what Dropbox is
by now it's almost a noun and Dropbox
originated as the the magic folder so
Dropbox is a folder on your computer
that you put files in and then distinct
to all your devices they're synced to
the cloud
since then Dropbox is working a lot of
features around collaboration and kind
of getting work done but at the core of
business there's a lot of storage that
goes on and what I work on Dropbox is
this storage part of the equation can
you give us any data about how big
Dropbox is how many users how much data
yes certainly I can I can
give you kind of the latest public
figures that we release I think we've
said we have over 500 million users so
it's a pretty big number I think over
200,000 businesses they used Dropbox for
their work in terms of actual data scale
itself the last number we really saw a
long time ago now was a billion files
synced per day and that that's obviously
grown over time and in terms of the the
magnitude of the storage itself we have
multiple exabytes of data and a storage
systems you know which would put us in
you know one of the biggest storage
providers in the world what unique
requirements does dropbox create on your
infrastructure in every large-scale
infrastructure company has different
requirements and so if you look at
companies like Google it's a very
compute heavy company companies like
Facebook latency matters a lot to them
they have quite compute heavy some of
that data is quite ephemeral it's its
news posts that you might see for a
brief period of time for Dropbox people
entrust the most important files to us
so we a very storage heavy we have a lot
of a lot of storage at Dropbox
also we have very high requirements on
durability and availability and you can
imagine if you're putting your your
business documents or your passport
scans or all that kind of information
that you absolutely can't lose and you
need it whenever there's an incident for
example that means that for Dropbox
these really intense focus on durability
correctness and availability in these
were the kind of design constraints the
wind to building this the storage system
itself tell us about the history of
Dropbox prior to building your own
infrastructure yes so Dropbox has been
around for its close to 10 years now and
fortunately from the very beginning drop
up to is what we'd call a hybrid
architecture it was a very wise move
made was and accidentally wise moved
back to him it was very early on but you
know the very first version of Dropbox
ran on drew Halston's I see CEO yeah he
ran on his computer his laptop right and
then pretty soon afterwards running on a
single server and we had too much
stories to run him a single computer and
we used s3
for the storage so very early on even
from the very beginning the storage was
on Amazon s3 but all the business logic
was on our own service and as the
company grew naturally into a real
business with you know hundreds of
millions of users the scale of that
metadata and the business logic
increased over time to the point where
we have multiple data centers running
thousands of database machines multiple
petabytes of metadata and all the
compute that goes along with that but
still leveraging the storage of Amazon
s3 and and various other services local
user Amazon has a huge suite of products
and we're very open about you know you
leveraging third parties where it makes
sense so stuff like SCS and SQS and a
whole bunch of acronyms of start and end
in s that we've used to come to leverage
to build our business out briefly
describe what is s 3 s 3 is Amazon
simple storage service and it's a it's a
storage as a service platform you know
it provides an API to put files and
retrieve files and and many many
companies on the internet use Amazon to
handle their storage and it's a it's a
very wise move you know it's any company
should focus on their core competencies
right leveraging the skills that they're
uniquely good at for most companies
they're not uniquely good a story
stories requires a lot of specialized
skill sets a lot of teams that a lot of
companies don't have capacity management
teams and hardware teams etc and
leveraging a third pile like Amazon
makes a lot of sense for them it made a
lot of sense for Dropbox for a
considerable period of time but only got
to the point where we were really one of
the biggest players in the storage game
that it makes sense for us to invest in
building our own storage platform and
tailoring it better to our use cases so
you know better user experience you know
better performance low latency better
resource utilization etc because we're
at the scale where we we could do things
better for our use cases do you wanted
to do things better for your own use
cases according to all those criteria
that you just named now in what respect
was it not possible or maybe not
cost-effective to do that on s/3 s/3
really did give us
new performance and so one of the kind
of unintended consequences that came out
of his story is it it was sense perspex
pitched as a story of Dropbox's exodus
from the cloud
you know Dropbox is a cloud provider
ourselves right and we're quite
enthusiastic about cloud services we use
Amazon still for many of a lot of our
business but it got to a certain point
where we could do bit better you know
for example s3 has a hard job and they
have to provide a storage service that
works for every startup out there in the
world all right
most of those companies are much smaller
than Dropbox there's much smaller data
volumes and they have their own unique
workloads for Dropbox and I very
intimately what our workload looks like
I know if you upload a file to Dropbox
that you know there's a spike in reads
in the first hour that drops off at a
certain point the tapers off over a
certain kind of gradient over time we
know how big those those blocks normally
add that that make that comprise these
files and that information allows us to
build a story system that's tailored
very closely to our workloads so you
know storage systems where you can over
time use the kind of the the minimal
level of CPU overhead and RAM and
network to provide the kind of
guarantees you want to your customers
that's advantageous from a cost
perspective but particularly is also
advantageous from a technical
perspective we have three to five times
lower latency across our percentiles and
we did an s3
that said we're pretty happy with that
latency already on the back end it also
provides a platform that we can use to
build new features we can place data
close to our users now because we have
control exactly where we put that data
in the country we can use all the
tooling that came out of that project in
the tooling the monitoring the capacity
management etc
to build new products inside Dropbox new
infrastructure products so it was a big
kind of leveling up of the
infrastructure team here but it really
came from a situation where we felt what
we could have a competitive advantage
and we could do better and not that they
would that dissatisfied with the status
quo already I'm gonna say something I
believe condenses several points you
made here and you tell me if this is
what you actually said the typical
application
doesn't create any specialized needs on
infrastructure the typical cloud
provider is gonna provide a range of
general purpose machines that work most
of the time if you're small and it
doesn't quite fit what you do it's okay
because you make do with what you have
but there's a point where you become so
large that the gap between what you're
getting and what you could build
yourself if you really optimized it
justifies taking on this huge cost to
make something that's just right for you
yeah I mean the magic pocket story
sparked a lot of conversations and hack
and use in these various places and
there were great conversations but a lot
of the comments of people saying stuff
like you're an idiot if you use a cloud
provider because it's so expensive and
that's just not true right you know if
you want to build a storage service as
reliable as Amazon s3 it requires a lot
of investment right and for Dropbox for
example you know we store all user data
in multiple geographic regions we can
lose the entire East Coast and keep
running and have no data lots of no
availability issues that level of
durability and availability is a
significant step beyond what you'd get
from a small on-premise storage
operation and the likes of Amazon s3 the
world are kind of providing that level
of service to a large degree I
understand your rationale at the time
was this decision very clear within
Dropbox or was it controversial well at
the time if you think of when the
verdict originated it wasn't clear you
know it was it was a spur a ssin I mean
you know wouldn't it be great we could
build a storage system but it was
totally unclear at the time where the
rule capable of doing it at least
capable of doing so in the short term
and what would it what it would entail
and so our job as engineers was to take
controversy off the table right there
was no point where we were going to
launch a story system that was
controversial right it was no point
where we were going to go and say hey
guys we're deleting all our data from s3
we hope it's safe okay
and so our job was really to kind of
build a very smooth transition
trajectory where we ramped the system
out very slowly you're starting from
to engineers building a prototype and
experimenting and scaling it up it's a
very low resource of consumption just to
engineers right - you know eventually a
big team and and and and big hardware
purchases but these were all leverage on
previous experimental decisions and
increasing our confidence as we went so
by the time you know what you hear about
in that wide story was when we were
ramping up very fast
we will bring on 30 to 40 racks of of
storage a day and needs a very dense
storage towers these these are these
racks with multiple petabytes in them
it's just a very steep ramp in storage
but this is only once we've gone through
a very long proving period and during
that period we store dark we stored some
of our users both I'm magic pocket and
s3 while we gain that confidence I mean
this like extensive production
validation period where we made sure we
were absolutely confident from the
operational perspective that we could
keep this storage system running and we
could provide the kind of guarantees we
wanted so by the time we launched it it
was not totally uncontroversial but I
think we've been very controversial if
we decided on day one to build the
entire storage system flip everything
over in one day you mentioned a moment
ago that most organizations don't have a
lot of expertise in infrastructure or
especially in storage which is in
specialized niche of infrastructure did
you have the skills you needed within
the company or were you having to hire
to bring in specialists who knew about
building this type of system yeah one of
the interesting interesting things that
came out this project was just the
breadth of roles I think you don't even
realize you need early on and when we
started we had a lot of smart driven
engineers who had a good grasp of
distributed systems and architecture etc
but we didn't have an extensive hardware
team we didn't have hard drive experts
we didn't have a large networking team
with experience in backbone networks and
metro networks and transit and peering
all that kind of stuff we didn't have a
capacity management team and that's you
know that's one of the interesting
things you know you can you can imagine
running out of space on your hard drive
on your local and your laptop is a
pretty big deal you obviously can't run
out of space on a multi exabyte storage
system and so there's a lot of supply
chain management goes into
I remember a time when we were ramping
up the system very quickly we're adding
maybe five plus petabytes a day and we
had two trucks crash in one week so we
had to big contract the trailers
delivering racks they both crashed in
one week the drivers were fine but we
lost a lot of storage hardware that
could have a crippled a company that
didn't have a very mature supply chain
organization that already baked these
assumptions in you know being able to
deal with vendor shortages etc so
there's all these rolls that you don't
expect I think ahead of time but
fortunately we were able to hire up a
lot of great people to help help build
this and that team really went from
originally was a small group of
engineers to being a really quite large
multidisciplinary team over time you
mentioned the network engineering
component my experience with Amazon is
that you can get a server from them and
it'll be the server you want it has
certain amount of memory storage they'll
make some guarantees about the
performance of the storage and you have
a lot of control over the server but the
network is more opaque and it's yeah
less clear what it is they're promising
you how much was gaining control over
the network important in order to
deliver the end product he wanted well
it was important in various ways one way
it was important is because we have
multiple services the Dropbox you know
we have storage but we have all sorts of
person that goes on on that storage you
know for example if you upload a word
document to Dropbox we generate a PDF
preview of that Word document for you so
that if you try to view it on your phone
and you don't have word installed we can
show you a render of that document and
you can read it there's all sorts of
things that go on behind the scenes to
make Dropbox like a very seamless user
experience if you upload a video we
h.264 encode the first five seconds of
that video so we can start streaming it
to you on your phone or on your laptop
so we have a lot of services that read
data a Dropbox and process that etc so
being able to co-locate them with the
storage was advantageous being able to
have management of our peering
relationships was advantageous you can
imagine the amount of the volume of data
we push the Dropbox is huge it's in the
terabytes of network capacity
so there's a lot of investment in kind
of the efficiencies within a network
stack you know on topic networks and now
the interesting part was just getting
the data into the storage system to
begin with and so there was a six-month
period where we brought over 500
petabytes into the storage system out of
Amazon and into the storage system and
so that you can do the math and this
this is hundreds of hundreds of gigabits
non-stop of traffic moving into the
storage system and and that was only
possible with kind of very close
relationships with Amazon and peering
relationships etc to pull that kind of
volume of traffic into the system liked
a shift now and talked about the magic
pocket system before I ask you about the
system I'm a more of a meta question
what were some of the principles and
philosophies that guided your design
thinking everyone who's involved in the
project is familiar with other storage
systems that have been built there's
only certain number of ways to build a
storage system and you know we familiar
with distributed systems literature and
so you we all have a good architectural
sense for how to design their systems
it's a big gulf from designing system in
theory to actually pulling it off in
practice and and one thing that we're
well aware of is that you have to build
really simple systems because the
complexity comes over time you know when
you have literally hundreds of thousands
of nodes in the system
it just gets complex no matter how
simple you design it so I guess the most
important principle well there's two
really important principles one less
important principles was keep it simple
like every design component had to be
really simple not over optimized not
over thought one example of that is
early on we have we have any storage
index in our storage we have multiple
tiers of storage indexes indices but one
of those maps a block to this logical
place in within the system is a Miss
huge database and originally we had
planned to build our own in-memory key
value store a huge one for performance
reasons but we decided you know what
let's just use a big mass sequel
database does use a big shadow my sequel
cluster is too much to think about right
now to design our own key value store at
the same time
we have a lot of expertise in running my
sequel databases let's just use it big
shadow my sequel database to this part
of the system
you know we plan on replacing that but
it turned out they looked great and we
still use this giant database it works
perfectly and that just saved the
complexity of a custom in-house key
value store that we didn't need right
the other principle is going to get to
is is what we call in the team a hundred
percent correctness or getting to zero
right and that means we need to ask
ourselves at any point in time is this
system correct like is every piece of
data in the system valid correct
uncorrupt
right and we want to be able to say no
absolute certainty and have have
constant verification systems that that
can verify this and if there's ever a
spike in that graph that ever changes we
know something went wrong right and so
having that verification coverage and
knowing it everything's correct today
gives us like a lot of insight into
correctness moving forward and this
sounds like an obvious thing but if you
kind of ask her out people who've been
in the industry for a while most
databases and storage systems have a lot
of inconsistencies in them you know all
that data it looks weird because five
years ago Bob did something bla and it's
very easy that noise to inhibit your
visibility into the behavior of the
system so for us
absolute zero compromised on on errors
in production there's always errors in
in testing we're human beings you know
but you have this this big release
process with very stringent verification
coverage to make sure that every bit in
those discs is correct you know every
bitten index Maps correctly to the discs
themselves and in terms of building the
system that meant more code I'm having
seen the lying counts recently but I
would guess it a similar amount of code
goes into verification coverage probably
more code goes into verifiers
than the storage system itself this
makes a point that invariants help you
reason about a system do you agree with
that absolutely they help you move
faster as well you know I think if
you're prototyping startup and you just
gotta move fast and get stuff done
that's fun
maybe the invariants will slow you down
for a couple of days
if you're building a large system that
has to be durable with you know 12 plus
9s of durability the invariance and the
test coverage make you move faster you
know it's much much easier to push code
because you know you're gonna be a
detective Airy quickly if there's an
issue and that's something we invested
in early on it really paid huge
dividends and and there's actually a
technical blog where we go into the
verification stack on the job architect
blog that people can check out a lot of
examples of the kind of verifiers we
used so we need to have to trust our
disks with storing the right data for
example I'll make sure we link to that
blog post in the show notes searching
for a new job is stressful and scary
then you go through the interview
process only to find the salary offer or
company culture doesn't match what
you're looking for
hired comm is the world's most
intelligent talent matching platform for
engineering we make your job search
faster and stress-free
after completing the application top
employers apply to hire you you receive
personalized interview requests and
upfront salary information your
dedicated advocate will assist you
providing career coaching to help you
with potential employers hired calm
hides your profile from current and past
employers to respect your privacy
the best part it's always free today is
se Radio listeners can earn a $2,000
hiring bonus by signing up at hire calm
/ se radio find your next chapter at
hired comm / se way
so what are the main use cases of the
system the main use case of magic pocket
is storing users files the vast majority
of what stored in magic pocket is files
users uploaded and serving them to users
when they request to view them here
writes and reads writes and reads it's a
it's an unusual workload because most
people think of storage systems as
having a very high breed to write ratio
you know you write something once but
you read it a lot with Dropbox we have
an unusual scenario we have one of the
world's largest caches which is people's
computers at home right people have
their Dropbox account but their files
are typically on the only local laptop
as well so a lot of the reads are served
locally off their computers so within
the storage system itself we've a much
close to the 50/50 ratio or reads the
writes it's a very right heavy system
let's talk about the architecture give
an overview of the architecture of the
magic pocket system it's a big system
and so it's hard to describe in detail
people who know the tech blog to see the
architecture but I'll give you some kind
of some fundamental principles so the
first is there's concepts called a zone
and a zone of the geographic region and
they're completely autonomous opaque
geographic regions and we make sure that
all data is in at least two zones the
two zones run different versions of code
their operational scripts aren't allowed
to run across two zones simultaneously
and that's our hedge against large-scale
disasters you know a meteor hitting a
city or someone operated running a
really bad script that manages it too
can destroy a zone then within a zone we
have an architecture where you have an
index that map's a block and blocks a
portion of a file to multiple locations
on disk and there's a lot more
components in it but essentially as
simple as that you know an index this
block is replicated this many times on
disk now the live writes they come in to
the system and we we pick a number of
random disks to write to to spread that
data around across multiple racks and
rows and and facilities
for physical redundancy and then in the
background we erase your code that data
so we apply something similar to an
algorithm could read Solomon to give us
the same level of redundancy of storage
redundancy but with a lower level of
storage overhead and for us that's one
of the games you've gotta play is you
can't compromise and durability you have
to be able to handle a large number of
correlated hard drive failures but you
want to do that with the minimum number
of of hard drives no one wants to be
wasting storage let me see if I
understand this a file comes in the file
if it's big enough it'll be split into
blocks this index which is the my sequel
sharted index tracks the mapping of
Roberts file to a bunch of different
blocks which are on different hard
drives throughout the zone and then you
copy it over to another zone just to
make sure you've got to copy exactly so
you have four redundancy within his own
each cernan's has very high durability
we've never lost data within a zone but
we had those two zones they just for the
disaster scenario and then you have
internal processes that deal
automatically with failures because in
system like this failure is used to norm
fail is not an unusual event when you
have hundreds of thousands of disks they
fail every day this is the disk life
lifecycle and so the system designed to
automatically replicated over this a
failure so if you lose a disk the
systems that detect that make sure that
data is very quickly rear applicated
elsewhere in the system and to a large
extent it's it's the hands-off operation
you know we've developed the operational
maturity right now that the system
manages itself to a very large extent
you know we go through a disk
remediation lifecycle we talk about
where I'll give you an example of this
so you can't have operators manually
attacking disk failures and you don't
want operators on scooters some
companies do this but we certainly no
want people on scooters writing on the
data center pulling disks in a hurry and
putting replacements in because that's
that's open to operator error right you
don't want operators having to do
anything on a live system so if you lose
a disk we let it fail the disk was dead
and we have some some systems
automatically try to recover it you know
maybe it's a bad sector
you repaired that sector bring it up
again if there's a bad file system maybe
to repair that file system bring it up
again
after a number of attempts the system
detects this disk was bad something
wrong with this disk it weights the data
to be fully replicated so we know that
there's no dependency on that disk you
know we have want a disk to a lab and
try to get stuff of it you know it's
fully replicated elsewhere at that point
mark that disk is gone and the system
keeps running and only very infrequently
that system also files a ticket the data
center operation of folks that
eventually they can come around you know
asynchronously and replace this ledger
in bulk and and you destroy them on site
but there's no you know live manual
intervention required and that's very
important for durability if we lose if
we lose a disk on a long weekend we
don't want to be vulnerable to data loss
because we're waiting for an operator to
come around and swap it out everything's
automatically replicated very quickly I
understand from Y Magazine you design
your own servers tell us about what what
why did why could you not use existing
servers why do you have to build your
own yeah yes so this is something else
that comes in in that kind of timeline
of expertise you know at first you've
got your hands full just designing a
system building the operation of tooling
to get it working but at certain point
that's bad because stable and you can
start focusing on on the hardware
profile so up into this point you view
hardware is a black black box yeah yes
this is software engineering radio we we
think hard about how was just you
probably think you write something to a
disc and the disc actually stores it oh
yeah it doesn't do that right it says it
does but it doesn't yes so at a certain
point you have to stop seeing that that
hardware is a black box and actually
look through the stack and we were to
the point where we wanted to increase
that storage density primarily for cost
reasons and take advantage of the latest
generations of hardware so we had a
protocol discotheque in discotheque was
the disk technology team and and their
job really was to look across the stack
so what our first version of the system
just treated hard as a black box and we
had our file system on that disk and the
blobs that the blocks of data work were
packed into extent that was stored in
that fast
and the new system completely rewrote
the stack there's no file system we
directly schedule the disk ourselves we
issue GBC instruction codes to the disks
- - to schedule them we have our own
SSDs in the disk to do to do caching etc
and and that process allowed us to take
advantage of new technologies like SMA
and somehow the technology stands the
shingle magnetic recording that gives
you 30 plus percent more density of
storage density for lower cost but it's
primarily an append-only storage the
dynamics of how that this is laid out I
mean when you write a tract this leakage
into the adjacent rack and it performs
quite poorly for random writes so we
rewrote our storage system to be
append-only strictly and we had this
very close alignment between the
hardware team the software team to
design a storage chassis that meets our
needs we had a couple of these you know
you want to have a lot of diversity in
the IDE with profiles that you use but
we have this kind of platform what you
call a discothèque box which is a four
you rack mount server this stores a
little bit over a hundred drives and
they have varying disk densities as new
disks come out we adopt them but you can
think of these restoring over a petabyte
of data in a single for you back now
chassis and what is for you I say yes
sorry
so au is a unit it's a standard measure
of rack height
so a typical rack might be 40 you high
42 44 you high depending how tall you of
server rack is so you can store
depending on how big your rack is you
know between 8 and 11 for you servers in
a single rack and so you're talking you
know around 10 petabytes potentially 10
petabytes or more in a single rack in a
data center something I'm curious about
programmers are trained to think in
layers I we have to have layers because
it's a way to manage complexity yeah and
you think about the layer underneath you
it is a black box you have to trust that
it's gonna do what you think it's gonna
do and you focus on writing your layer
like you're saying software engineers we
think storages of black box
to what extent did your software
engineers need to really understand the
characteristics of the hardware in order
to implement something that would in the
end meet your requirements yeah yeah lay
violations are always ugly right we're
huge believers in strong api's and very
simple clean api's and to a large extent
you can avoid layer violations by
understanding that the the layer below
might fail to meet its obligations so
you might tell a dis to f sync that it
gets lost because of a sector error or
what have you and so you have
verification systems that span layers so
for us most of the verifies a kind of
cross layer verifiers to verify what we
think is correct on one layer is
correcting the layer above but there
were times where we had to yes work
across layers for example there's
hundreds of kind of facts that go into
the design of a storage system one isn't
in these SMR drives they typically have
these independent right zones they're
typically 256 megabytes wide and so we
wanted to make our extents that we put
on these disks multiples of 256
megabytes there's a lot of facts like
that and and nuances that went into the
kind of the architecture that and the
constants to go into the storage system
it's unfortunate to engage in late
violations and I think people should
avoid it it's best they can but at a
certain point when you really want to
eat out but efficiency I think it's
necessary but this is why I said early
in the podcast the complexity comes
right you have to have a really really
simple system because eventually you
start saying hey maybe we should start
using SMR drives rather than the current
PM our technology if you have a complex
storage system is absolutely no way you
can retrofit that in the complexity
comes as you go so I think focusing on
very very simple API is very very clean
layers allows an occasional layer
violation for performance reasons I want
to change the subject
talk about rust you've had a lot of code
written and go but you switched to rust
which we did a show recently on rust
what aspects of the go language were not
meeting your needs for this project yeah
so we've actually gone through three
languages on this project so the
original prototype was in Python discuss
we are
move fast and we'll just playing around
with architectures but once it became
clear we wanted to have a really durable
large scale system we rewrote it in go
in the strong type system helped a lot
there the concurrency support the memory
efficiency to a large extent we are very
happy with go and go is still the
primary infrastructure language at
Dropbox the only thing that language
here is that you know having a minimal
set of languages as advantageous right
you want to have common libraries and
minimize language proliferation but you
want to use the right tool for the job
right and then and then we use cases
where we wanted a more C++ like language
without having to use C++ one good
example was the OSD which is the
codename for the storage device and this
is a device where there's hundreds of
thousands of these and the minimum
amount of RAM and CPU we use the better
and so we want to have very explicit
memory management on those devices so we
wanted a non garbage collected language
but we could do a lot of a manual memory
handling you know a lot of developers
here love the type system that comes
with rust the lovely expressively that
of a type system and you know they wish
go had generics but personally I'm a
huge go fan myself and I primarily about
my coding and go but I think there are
some use cases very large scale or with
resource consumption is very important
where rust makes a lot of sense people
here love the language and they love to
use it was memory management the main
driver of choice of rust in those cases
yeah I think initially memory management
was the main driver at I mean what
version of go was that when we started
doing it's probably go one three and the
garbage collectors improved a lot since
then but we were suffering pretty
significantly due to GC pauses and kind
of buffer bloat that's much less of a
problem these days but still this is a
you can imagine the storage knows the
boxes that push you know terabytes very
frequently through the through the
system the handling very lives buffers
so we could get better memory management
doing it ourselves but like I said
personally I use go primarily yeah
myself this issue of GC pauses it's come
up in several of our shows we did a show
on latency which was mainly looking at
latency that users perceive
the user is waiting for some operation
which somewhere is getting queued up
behind garbage collection pause and that
translates into end user latency was it
end user latency that you were concerned
about or how did garbage collection
pauses at that deep of a layer turn into
a problem it's a stupid question because
the reality is they infrequently very
infrequently do they make it out to the
user because there's just so many layers
on top of the system and the volume to
dive you push them in are so large the
tip of the GC pause is not affecting
it's not like a database where you're
doing very high QPS primarily it was out
internal operations stuff like repair
traffic and pushing around live buffers
that were issues also just this -
keeping the size of the the free memory
pool under control was also was also an
issue for us on the list is yeah we do
we do see GC pause issues in Dropbox and
and we is a pretty crude solution with a
lot of these things we still run more
processors per box you know magic pocket
has the storage nodes but it has a lot
of serving traffic as well and you know
we run 16 processors per box sometimes
just to keep the heat pipe size smaller
for the sake of memory management and
minimize some GC pauses I've heard the
new version of go has a better garbage
collector again it's getting better
every day every day maybe we don't need
to do that anymore yeah but there's
something will experiment with soon to
talk now about the move how did you cut
over from s3 to magic pocket yeah very
gradually and very carefully and so for
the longest time we had some small
fraction of users say 10% I got to 30%
eventually that was stored
simultaneously in both magic pocket and
in s3 I remember the date very
viscerally because it's a big kind of
point of celebration when we began the
period called production validation and
so this point we had a fairly large
story system that could store around
about 30 percent of our data it was
running in multiple geographical regions
and we said okay from this day onwards
we're gonna treat this as a primary
storage system but we had the data in s3
just in case and those is absolute zero
tolerance policy fair
if any if magic pocket went down for any
reason we had to kind of reset this
launch clock that we had and we wanted
to run for some consider a period time
many months of uninterrupted seamless
operation there was one point time where
we did have to reset the clock and I can
go into more details on that but but
once we finished that production
validation we were very confident in the
blood of the system to scale and operate
durably and then it was a period of just
shouldn't say Jeff that was quite
difficult of logistics buying as much
hardware as we could and bring it up as
quick as we could and funneling daughter
into the storage system as fast as we
could since she said you could go into
more detail about that there must be a
good yeah yeah so one of the things you
want to do a system like this is to
protect yourself from yourself and we
all had you know we live and breathe
durability and correctness here we have
a vested interest in seeing the system
launch as well you know as engineers
we're so excited about the system we
want to launch it right so we didn't
want to have any slippery slope
arguments so we decided before we went
to production validation we very little
contact for ourselves and we shared it
with with the Dropbox founders and it
was you know here's the conditions for
production validation and here's the
reasons we'll reset that clock you know
any major outages any major bugs and
make it to production any data
corruption anything like this and so we
had this big long list and that's the
point in time probably a month and a
half into production validation we're a
bug made it to our staging cluster so we
having your test testing cluster then
eventually the data graphs were staging
cluster which stores a copy of data and
then it goes to our production clusters
and dad I got a bug got that far and it
didn't actually cause any data loss
there's no data loss but we kind of got
lucky yeah we didn't we didn't see
coming we didn't catch that bug we have
verifies didn't detect it and it
happened and we hadn't violated the
rules of the production validation but
we all felt a little bit dirty about you
know getting a free pass and so we went
to kill who's a VP of engineering and
said hey kill we want to reset the clock
and he said great you know proud of you
guys kind of thing and we really said
and we started again that was a cost
money you know that that pushed the
launch of the system back
quite a lot but I think we wanted to
launch a system in a place where we
really you know unconditionally
confident in it and not not confident by
technicality
I'd like to wrap up here with some
questions about lessons learned and what
we can take away from this
in retrospect what were some of the
major lessons that you learned from this
migration uh-huh a lot of them out one
one of my favorite examples is just you
know when I was doing my PhD in
distributed systems I just didn't have a
grasp of the real world in terms of it
being people and bits and hardware all
right and that some of the problems
you're gonna face is stuff like the
cooling system breaking or a truck
crashing or we had a problem where we
just couldn't fit anymore racks in the
loading dock
that was like we couldn't put any more
Hardware because the loading dock was
full so there's a lot of when you get
into the real world the practical
realities and make making much more
exciting they're much more difficult now
that's one of lessons learned I think in
hindsight if you think what we would
have done differently the product went
well but I do wish we'd invested earlier
on in operational automation so the
longest time it was fairly stressful to
be an engineer in the project because
there's a lot of things a lot of
hardware braking a lot of manual
intervention
a lot of if you had that many boxes they
break it off just a weird of wonderful
ways and we had to manually fix them and
that was very distracting it kept
slowing down our progress and eventually
we hired some folks who had a lot of
experience in a lot of automation around
this and put a very strong SRE team at a
site reliability engineering team who
took over building tooling to automate
all these processes and that got us to a
point where we had much better
correctness because we know operators
can manually involved but also we could
focus on actually building things and so
I wish earlier on we done that but it
worked out fine in the end and I think
the last is this something you mentioned
earlier on which is that the importance
of simplicity it systems get really
complicated you know never do something
caused it because it looks cool or it
seems fun right you know I think within
the team the culture
if you could get away with not building
a system then don't build it right
because what matters first and foremost
is achieving the goals which is building
is having a durable storage system if
there wasn't off-the-shelf product that
worked great
you better believe you would have used
it but there wasn't right and so I think
keeping it as simple as possible because
like as I said the complexity comes with
time most of us are not ever going to be
involved in migrating exabytes of data
from one storage system to another but
it is very common that you need to move
off of an old system onto a new system
happens all the time what are some
advice you would give to people who are
in that kind of process that they could
learn from your experience yeah I think
the number one is always have an undo
button you want to never get rid of the
original source until you just
incredibly confident in the new one and
no matter how well you design it
architecture there's going to be
operational issues that slow you down so
I think doing that change in a way that
can be seamless is really important for
us that meant having a system where we
could seamlessly migrate users across
without them knowing and the other one
is that every engineer wants to redesign
something right as it's very it's very
natural impulse for engineer to want to
build something from scratch because
everyone likes building new systems and
instead of maintaining systems then
people should think very carefully
before they do that they should have a
very good reason for why to rebuild it
because the design is gonna be a lot
better it's gonna be much more efficient
these reasons and you know a lot of
migrations I think come in a situation
where it wasn't necessary all right but
I think this isn't like this RIA where
it was made a lot of sense for us to
build a system on our own
the big key was you know doing it slowly
and having a lot of opportunities to
turn back if anything went wrong I think
that's a great place to stop I James
cowling thank you so much for speaking
to software engineering radio okay it's
not to be a thanks so much you can reach
us with feedback by email team at SCO
radio net on Twitter at SC radio our
Facebook and our LinkedIn groups for
software engineering radio this has been
Robert
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website @ SC -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on twitter at SC
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team @ SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of SC radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]